<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="info" ipr="full3978" docName="oauth-consumer_request-1_0.xml">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc private="Implementers' Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title>Using OAuth for Consumer Requests</title>

    <author initials="E" surname="Hammer-Lahav" fullname="Eran Hammer-Lahav">
      <organization>Yahoo!</organization>
      <address>
        <email>eran@hueniverse.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="19" month="September" year="2008"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This memo describes a method for using the OAuth flow to sign
        a request made between a Consumer and Service Provider without User
        involvement, which is either absent or handled by other means.
        It enables OAuth to be used as a replacement to HTTP
        Basic authentication and extends the capabilities of the OAuth Consumer
        credentials.
      </t>
      <t>
        OAuth Core 1.0 defines a protocol for delegating user access to
        Consumer applications without sharing the user's private credentials.
        The protocol centers on a three-legged scenario, delegating User
        access to a Consumer for resources held by a Service Provider. In
        many cases, a two-legged scenario is needed, in which the Consumer
        is acting on behalf of itself, without a direct or any User involvement.
      </t>
      <t>
        OAuth was created to solve the problem of sharing two-legged credentials
        in three-legged situations. However, within the OAuth context, Consumers
        might still need to communicate with the Service Provider using requests
        that are Consumer-specific. Since the Consumers already established a
        Consumer Key and Consumer Secret, there is value in being able to use
        them for requests where the Consumer identity is being verified.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

    <section title="Notation and Conventions">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
        Domain name examples use <xref target="RFC2606" />.
      </t>
      <t>
        Unless otherwise noted, this specification is written as a direct
        continuation of <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" />, inheriting the definitions and
        guidelines set by it.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Consumer Identity">
      <t>
        This memo defines a method in which the Consumer Key and Consumer
        Secret, established by means left unspecified, are used to authenticate
        a Consumer against credentials stored by the Service Provider. For the
        purpose of this memo, it is assumed the Consumer already established
        a Consumer Key and Consumer Secret with the Service Provider.
      </t>
      <t>
        While the method described in this memo can be used with an empty
        Consumer Secret, it does not provide any security or protection in such
        a scenario, unless other means of identification are used, such as a
        Public Key.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Consumer Request">
      <t>
        The Consumer requests the Protected Resource by making an HTTP(S) request
        to the Service Provider. The request HTTP method and URI are provided by
        the Service Provider by means not specified in this memo. This workflow
        is identical to the one used to access a Protected Resource in
        a three-legged OAuth flow as defined in <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" />
        section 7.
      </t>

      <section title="Consumer Sends Request">
        <t>
          To access a Protected Resource, the Consumer sends an HTTP(S) request to
          the Service Provider's resource endpoint URI. The request MUST be
          signed as defined in <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" /> section 9 with an
          empty Token Secret. The request contains the following REQUIRED
          parameters, unless otherwise noted:

          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="oauth_consumer_key:">
              The Consumer Key.
            </t>
            <t hangText="oauth_token:">
              MUST be included with an empty value to indicate this is a two-legged request.
            </t>
            <t hangText="oauth_signature_method:">
              The signature method the Consumer used to sign the request.
            </t>
            <t hangText="oauth_signature:">
              The signature as defined in
              <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" /> section 9: Signing Requests.
            </t>
            <t hangText="oauth_timestamp:">
              As defined in <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" /> section 8: Nonce
              and Timestamp.
            </t>
            <t hangText="oauth_nonce:">
              As defined in <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" /> section 8: Nonce
              and Timestamp.
            </t>
            <t hangText="oauth_version:">
              OPTIONAL. If present, value MUST be <spanx style="verb">1.0</spanx>. Service Providers
              MUST assume the protocol version to be <spanx style="verb">1.0</spanx> if this parameter
              is not present. Service Providers' response to non-<spanx style="verb">1.0</spanx> value
              is left undefined.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Additional parameters:">
              OPTIONAL. Any additional parameters, as defined by the Service Provider.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Service Provider Replies">
        <t>
          The Service Provider verifies the signature and Consumer identity as
          defined in <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" /> section 9. If successful,
          it replies with the appropriate response to the Consumer request. The
          format of the reply is left unspecified by this memo.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the request fails verification or is rejected for other reasons,
          the Service Provider SHOULD respond with the appropriate response
          code as defined in <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" /> section 10: HTTP
          Response Codes. The Service Provider MAY include some further details
          about why the request was rejected in the HTTP response body as
          defined in  <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" /> section 5.3: Service
          Provider Response Parameters.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        This memo abides by the security considerations specified in
        <xref target="OAuth Core 1.0" />.
      </t>
    </section>

    <appendix title="Appendix A - Example">
      <t>
        In this example, the Service Provider <spanx style="verb">provider.example.net</spanx> is an
        OAuth-enabled website, and the Consumer <spanx style="verb">consumer.example.com</spanx> uses
        resources offered by the Service Provider on behalf of its Users.
        The Service Provider allows Consumers to manage their Consumer profile
        which includes their name and description using an API call, in
        addition to a manual HTML page. The Consumer profile is used by the
        Service Provider when asking Users to grant Consumer access.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Service Provider allows Consumers to see their profile at the
        following endpoint URI:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Profile Request URI:">
            <spanx style="verb">http://provider.example.net/profile</spanx>, using HTTP <spanx style="verb">GET</spanx>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The Service Provider supports the <spanx style="verb">HMAC-SHA1</spanx>
        signature method and the OAuth Authorization Header. No additional
        parameters are defined for the profile request.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Consumer already has an established identity with the Service
        Provider:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Consumer Key:">
            <spanx style="verb">dpf43f3p2l4k3l03</spanx>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Consumer Secret:">
            <spanx style="verb">kd94hf93k423kf44</spanx>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The consumer needs to sign the request before sending it to the Service
        Provider. To generate the signature, it first needs to generate the
        Signature Base String. The request contains the following parameters
        (<spanx style="verb">oauth_signature</spanx> excluded) which are
        ordered and concatenated into a normalized string:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="oauth_consumer_key:">
            <spanx style="verb">dpf43f3p2l4k3l03</spanx>
          </t>
          <t hangText="oauth_token:">
            (Empty value)
          </t>
          <t hangText="oauth_signature_method:">
            <spanx style="verb">HMAC-SHA1</spanx>
          </t>
          <t hangText="oauth_timestamp:">
            <spanx style="verb">1191242096</spanx>
          </t>
          <t hangText="oauth_nonce:">
            <spanx style="verb">kllo9940pd9333jh</spanx>
          </t>
          <t hangText="oauth_version:">
            <spanx style="verb">1.0</spanx>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The following inputs are used to generate the Signature Base String:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t hangText="The HTTP request method:">
            <spanx style="verb">GET</spanx>
          </t>
          <t hangText="The request URI:">
            <spanx style="verb">http://provider.example.net/profile</spanx>
          </t>
          <t hangText="The encoded normalized request parameters string:">
            <spanx style="verb">oauth_consumer_key=dpf43f3p2l4k3l03&amp;oauth_nonce=kllo9940pd9333jh&amp;oauth_signature_method=HMAC-SHA1&amp;oauth_timestamp=1191242096&amp;oauth_token=&amp;oauth_version=1.0</spanx>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The Signature Base String is:

        <figure>
          <artwork>
    GET&amp;http%3A%2F%2Fprovider.example.net%2Fprofile&amp;oauth_consumer_key%3Ddpf43f3p2l4k3l03%26oauth_nonce%3Dkllo9940pd9333jh%26oauth_signature_method%3DHMAC-SHA1%26oauth_timestamp%3D1191242096%26oauth_token%3D%26oauth_version%3D1.0
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        <spanx style="verb">HMAC-SHA1</spanx> produces the following <spanx style="verb">digest</spanx> value as a base64-encoded
        string, using the Signature Base String as <spanx style="verb">text</spanx> and
        <spanx style="verb">kd94hf93k423kf44&amp;</spanx> as <spanx style="verb">key</spanx> (empty
        Token Secret):

        <figure>
          <artwork>
    IxyYZfG2BaKh8JyEGuHCOin/4bA=
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        All together, the Consumer request for its profile is:

        <figure>
          <artwork>
            http://provider.example.net/profile

            Authorization: OAuth realm="http://provider.example.net/",
            oauth_consumer_key="dpf43f3p2l4k3l03",
            oauth_signature_method="HMAC-SHA1",
            oauth_signature="IxyYZfG2BaKh8JyEGuHCOin%2F4bA%3D",
            oauth_timestamp="1191242096",
            oauth_token="",
            oauth_nonce="kllo9940pd9333jh",
            oauth_version="1.0"
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        <spanx style="verb">provider.example.net</spanx> checks the signature and responds with the
        requested profile.
      </t>
    </appendix>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="References">

      <reference anchor="OAuth Core 1.0">
        <front>
          <title>OAuth Core 1.0</title>
          <author initials="" surname="OAuth Core Workgroup" fullname="OAuth Core Workgroup">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://oauth.net/core/1.0" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2606">
        <front>
          <title>Reserved Top Level DNS Names</title>
          <author initials="D.E" surname="Eastlake" fullname="D. Eastlake">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="A.P" surname="Panitz" fullname="A. Panitz">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2606" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials="B.S" surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
            <organization>Alis Technologies</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>
