<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2606 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2606.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2616 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'>
]
>
<?rfc authorship="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc private="Draft 2"?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="full3978" docName="oauth-ext-lang-pref-draft-02">
   <front>
      <title abbrev="xoauth-lang-pref-draft-1">
	    OAuth Extension for Specifying User Language Preference - Draft 2</title>
      <author initials="GF" surname="Fletcher" fullname="George Fletcher">
         <organization>AOL LLC</organization>
            <address>
               <email>gffletch@aol.com</email>
            </address>
         </author>
         <date month="December" year="2007"/>
         <area>OAuth Extension</area>
         <keyword>OAuth</keyword>
         <keyword>Extension</keyword>
         <keyword>Language Preference</keyword>
         <keyword>Draft</keyword>
         <abstract>
            <t>This memo describes how the Consumer and Service Provider can
	    communicate the user's preferred language preference.</t>
         </abstract>
      </front>
      <middle>
         <section anchor="contrib" title="Contributors">
            <t>
               <list style='empty'>
               	  <t>Allen Tom</t>
                  <t>Eran Hammer-Lahav</t>
                  <t>John Kemp</t>
                  <t>Joseph Holsten</t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="conv" title="Notation and Conventions">
            <t>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, 
	    “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”, “SHOULD NOT”, “RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, 
	    and “OPTIONAL” in this document are to be interpreted as 
	    described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>. Domain name examples use 
	    <xref target="RFC2606"/>.</t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="defs" title="Definitions">
            <t>
               <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="Service Provider:">A web application that allows 
	      access via OAuth.</t>
                  <t hangText="Consumer:">A website or application that uses 
	      OAuth to access the Service Provider on behalf of the User.</t>
                  <t hangText="User:">An individual who has an account with the 
	      Service Provider.</t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="desc" title="Description">
            <t>In certain cases it is necessary or prudent for the Consumer 
            to specify to the Service Provider the language preference of 
	    the user so that UI presented during the user authorization 
	    phase is presented in the preferred language of the user.</t>
            <t>This language preference specification should be interpreted
	    by the Service Provider as a UI/UE recommendation. The goal is
	    to provide a better experience for the user.</t>
            <t>Note that this is NOT the language preference of the Service 
	    Provider.</t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="parameter" title="Parameter Specification">
            <t>The OAuth Language Preference MUST be specified with the 
	    parameter name 'xoauth_lang_pref'. The value of the parameter 
	    MUST conform to the rules for the Accept-Language HTTP header 
	    in <xref target="RFC2616"/>.
            <list>
                  <t>xoauth_lang_pref = 1#( language-range [ ";" "q" "=" qvalue ] )</t>
                  <t>language-range  = ( ( 1*8ALPHA *( "-" 1*8ALPHA ) ) | "*" )</t>
               </list>
            </t>
            <t>As this can be in the query params or form data it will also 
	    then need to be appropriately URL-encoded for transmission and 
	    decoded for use by the recipient.</t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="ext-uri" title="Extension Identifier">
            <t>The Service Provider can advertise that it supports this
	    extension by listing the following URI in the public documentation
	    that also describes the public endpoints. In addition, if the
	    Service Provider supports the <xref format="none" target="oauth_disco_1_0">[OAuth Discovery 1.0]</xref>
	    specification, then this URI must be listed for each endpoint where 
	    the Service Provider will process the parameter.
	    <list>
                  <t>http://oauth.net/ext/language_preference/1.0</t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="processing" title="Processing Rules">
            <t>The Consumer MAY specify the language preference of the user by 
	    adding the xoauth_lang_pref parameter to any Service Provider endpoint that
	    supports the extension.</t>
            <t>The Service Provider MUST document publicly which
	    endpoints support the extension.</t>
            <t>The Service Provider SHOULD specify which enpoints support the
            Language Preference extension via the <xref format="none" target="oauth_disco_1_0">[OAuth Discovery 1.0]</xref>
            specification.</t>
            <t>The recipient of the xouath_lang_pref parameter MAY combine 
	    the language preferences found in that parameter with those 
	    present in any available Accept-Language HTTP header to determine 
	    the language preference list of the user (by virtue of any 
	    supplied 'quality values' (see <xref target="RFC2616"/>, section 14).</t>
            <t>The Consumer SHOULD consider using a higher 'quality value' if precedence
	    over the HTTP Accept-Language header is desired.</t>
            <t>If the Service Provider can not provide the UI in the
	    preferred language, then the Service Provider should attempt a
	    "best effort match" between the user's preferred languages and the
	    languages supported by the Service Provider. Definition of the 
	    "best effort match" algorithm is out of scope for this document.</t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="example" title="Examples">
            <t>Example xoauth_lang_pref with a single language
               <list>
                  <t><figure><artwork>xoauth_lang_pref="en-us"</artwork></figure></t>
               </list>
            </t>
            <t>Example xoauth_lang_pref with multiple values
         <list>
                  <t><figure><artwork>xoauth_lang_pref=en-gb;q=1.0, en-us;q=0.8</artwork></figure></t>
               </list>
            </t>
            <t>Example xoauth_lang_pref encoded for transport as query
	    string or form element
         <list>
                  <t><figure><artwork>xoauth_lang_pref=en-gb%3bq%3d1.0%2c+en-us%3bq%3d0.8</artwork></figure></t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>
         <section anchor="practice" title="Possible Use Cases">
            <section title="Language preference as part of Request Token request">
               <t>[The following flow is for explanatory purposes and describes only
               	one of many ways to accomplish the specified task.]</t>
               <t>In this use case the Consumer knows the user's language 
	      preference and chooses to specify it as part of the request for
	      the Request Token. By specifying the language preference on
	      this request, the Service Provider can either encode information
	      into the request token or potentially dynamically generate an
	      appropriate authorization URL. This last option requires the
	      support by both the Consumer and Service Provider of dynamically
	      generated authorization URLs.</t>
               <t>The basic flow would be...
            <list style="numbers">
                     <t>The user interacts with the Consumer in a way that allows
		the Consumer to know the user's language preference. It could
		also be that the Consumer only really supports a single 
		language and wants the user's experience to all be in the
		same language.</t>
                     <t>When the user requests access to a resource that requires
		authorization with a Service Provider, the Consumer generates
		the request for the request token and adds the xoauth_lang_pref
		parameter to those being sent to the Service Provider.</t>
                     <t>The Service Provider receives the request for the Request
		Token and processes the xoauth_lang_pref parameter.</t>
                     <t>The Service Provider encodes the chosen language
		preference from those specified or it's own default and
		associates the language preference with the generated request
		token.</t>
                     <t>The Consumer receives the request token and generates the
		authorization URL and redirects the user to the authorization
		endpoint at the Service Provider.</t>
                     <t>The Service Provider processes the request token and retrieves
		the associated language preference.</t>
                     <t>The Service Provider uses this language preference to display
		the UI for the user to authorize the resource access request.</t>
                  </list>
               </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Language preference as part of Authorization request">
               <t>[The following flow is for explanatory purposes and describes only
               	one of many ways to accomplish the specified task.]</t>
               <t>In this use case, the Consumer knows the user's language perference but
               	the Service Provider only supports acceptance of the xoauth_lang_pref 
               	parameter as part of the user authorization step. In handling the
               	authorization request, the Service Provider will process the xoauth_lang_pref
               	parameter and display the authorization UI in the "best effort match" of
               	the user's specified language preference and those languages supported
               	by the Service Provider.</t>
               	<t>The basic flow would be...
                <list style="numbers">
                     <t>The user interacts with the Consumer in a way that allows
		the Consumer to know the user's language preference. It could
		also be that the Consumer only really supports a single 
		language and wants the user's experience to all be in the
		same language.</t>
                     <t>When the user requests access to a resource that requires
		authorization with a Service Provider, the Consumer generates
		the request for the request token without specifying the
		xoauth_lang_pref parameter.</t>
                     <t>The Service Provider receives the request for the Request
		Token and processes per <xref format="none" target="oauth_core_1_0">[OAuth Core 1.0]</xref>.</t>
                     <t>The Consumer receives the request token and generates the
		authorization URL also appending the xoauth_lang_pref parameter.</t>
                     <t>The Service Provider processes the request token and language preference
                     	parameter.</t>
                     <t>The Service Provider determines the "best effort match" of requested
                     	language preferences and Service Provider supported languages and uses that 
                     	language to display the UI for the user to authorize the resource access request.</t>
                </list>
               </t>
            </section>
         </section>
      </middle>
      <back>
         <references>
      	&rfc2119;
      	&rfc2606;
      	&rfc2616;
      	<reference anchor="oauth_core_1_0">
               <front>
                  <title>OAuth Core 1.0</title>
                  <author initials="OCW" surname="OAuth" fullname="OAuth Core Workgroup">
                     <organization /></author>
                     <date day="4" month="December" year="2007"/>
                  </front>
                  <format type="HTML" target="http://oauth.net/core/1.0" /></reference>
                  <reference anchor="oauth_disco_1_0">
                     <front>
                        <title>OAuth Discovery 1.0 Draft 1</title>
                        <author initials="E" surname="Hammer-Lahav" fullname="Eran Hammer-Lahav">
                           <organization>Hueniverse, LLC</organization>
                           <address>
                              <email>eran@hueniverse.com</email>
                           </address>
                        </author>
                        <date day="12" month="December" year="2007"/>
                     </front>
                     <format type="HTML" target="http://oauth.googlecode.com/svn/spec/discovery/1.0/drafts/1/spec.html" /></reference>
                  </references>
               </back>
            </rfc>